The Right To Revolt

Keith Laumer

Worlds of IF – June 1971

First, can you keep from losing?

Then, can you keep from winning?

THEY were waiting for Andy Galt as he left the Weather Control Complex at the end of the Dawn Shift: Pinchot, sleek and dandified even in a Survey coverall. Williver, big and soft, with a worried look on his too-small face, Gray, lean as a ferret, bright-eyed, nervous, and Timmins, silent as usual.

“You’ve heard?” Pinchot said. “They did it.” Galt nodded.

“Some politico who’s never been within five lights of Colmar decides we need to open another hundred miles of desert,” Gray said. “So five hundred* of us are going to be drafted and shipped out to the plateau to play the hardy pioneer.”

“We knew they were going ahead,” Walt said, “Why act surprised?”

“There was always a chance they’d take our warning and back down,” Gray said. He had a thin, high voice, a mouth that seemed always to be grinning a secret grin.

“It couldn’t have been more blatant if they were trying to goad us beyond endurance,” Pinchot said. “It’s as if they were thumbing their noses and daring us to do something.”

“We told them,” Williver said, sounding frightened. He swallowed. “We held off until now to give them a chance to see reason. They didn’t. Opening a new sector now is a smack in the teeth to every man in the colony.”

“It’s not just a little kick in the mouth,” Gray said. “It’s slavery for all of us who are tagged to go out on the advance team. And for what? To give the Colonial Bureau a nice growth rate to brag about.”

“To fill politicians’ pockets back on Terra,” Pinchot corrected. “We’re supposed to give up our homes, families, friends, move out into the desert, live in lash-up hutments, eat issue rations, work like horses fourteen hours a day—”

“I’m not afraid of work,” Galt said. “If it were on a voluntary basis I might even sign on.”

“But it’s not voluntary, Galt. It’s compulsory. They decide who goes and for how long.”

“Even here in town it’s serfdom,” Gray said. “Look at you—with an advanced degree in administration—putting in your two years on a board at Weather like any clod. And Pinch, here, with a Master’s in personnel dynamics

“What about the petition, Pinchot?” Galt cut off the complaint impatiently. “Didn’t you get an answer?”

-

PINCHOT took a paper from an inside pocket, handed it over. It was a letter on the stationery of the Colonial Administrator, formally—and patronizingly, Galt thought—thanking the addressee for his interest in administration policy.

“It was addressed to me by name,” Pinchot said, “not to the Committee. Don’t ask me how they knew. But it doesn’t matter now.” He tore the letter in two and tossed it aside. “So much for appeals to established authority. We tried the peaceful way. Now we’re taking matters into our own hands. So—are you with us, Galt—or against us?”

“He doesn’t have to be either,” Timmins spoke up. “He’s got a right to be neutral.”

Pinchot shook his head. “Not any more,” he said. “The time’s come to take sides.”

“The Committee of Fifty,” Galt said, “consisting of forty-one members by actual count, out of over twenty-five thousand colonists—”

“What percentage of French peasants staged the French Revolution?” Gray demanded. “How many Americans actually fired on the Redcoats? How many Bolsheviks tossed out the Czar?”

“We do it,” Pinchot said, his eyes narrow and intent. “We move in fast, take the Port and the Comm Center, the generator and pumping stations, the depot and warehouses, grab Admin House—and we’re in charge.”

“What about the Security Force?”

“We’ll bottle them up in their barracks.”

“Spacearm could blow us off the planet.”

“But they won’t. BuCol wants profits, that means operating mines and plants. We’ll cooperate with them; they won’t get rough. They’ll accept the fait accompli.”

All heads turned as the soft whirr of a turbodyne sounded. A police cart came into view; the men stood silent as it coasted to a stop beside them. A tall, loose-jointed man in Security uniform swung down, sauntered over. He was a stranger, too tall, too pale, out from Terra, not a colonial.

“Let’s see your IDs. fellows,” he said in a nasal Terran accent. His partner sat stolidly on the cart, watching. The four colonists handed over their tags, which were scrutinized cursorily and handed back.

“What are you doing here?” the Security man asked in a lazy tone, as if he didn’t much care but was asking anyway. Gall felt his face tighten. He shook off Willis’ restraining hand.

“Minding our own business.” he said harshly. “Why?”

The Security man looked him over casually.

“Come over to the flat,” he said easily.

“What for?” Galt said.

“Move,” the cop snapped and flipped a small rod from his belt.

Galt walked over to the cart.

“Turn around, get your hands up behind your head.”

Galt followed orders. Careless hands slapped down his sides, deftly turned his pockets inside out. The Security man grunted.

“That’s all. Break it up now. I don’t want to see you hanging around in the streets after five bells.”

The cart rolled away. Pinchot came over, picked up the items the Security man had dropped on the pavement, handed them to Galt.

“They’re nice fellows.” he said softly. “just doing their job.”

“When?” Galt asked tightly.

“Tonight. Be at the Watergate at midnight, read} for action.” Pinchot said.

“I’ll be there.” Gall said.

-

WALKING through the dark street. Gall thought about it. He remembered stirring stories he’d read in grade school of hardy pioneers of half a century earlier his grandfather among them who had come out from Terra during the Population Riots to cast their lot for themselves and their families on the virgin world called Colmar.

It had been a terrifying crossing: five thousand men and women in the hold of a marginally spaceworthy freighter, packed like sardines with barely space to move, fed on minimal rations, three bodies alotted to each bunk, sharing community toilets, with no amusements, no privacy, no relief for the long months of the voyage.

And arriving at the end of it not on the soft, green world of open spaces and fresh air they’d been led to expect—but on the harsh bare rock of Colmar. There’d been riots then and some killing. But in the end the survivors had voted to stay, to take their chances on the new world, to conquer or die.

Very melodramatic, Galt thought to himself. But what’s it got to do with today? They worked out their lives to give us—their descendants—something better. But do we have it? We’ve seeded the oceans, made soil, planted crops. Today we can talk in the open air without respirators, eat our home-grown vegetables; we have a town with an auditorium, a sports arena and a public library …

“But we’re still slaves,” he said aloud. “We’ve been used; we dance to Terra’s tune. The best of our products go off-planet in return for a bare subsistence level of imports. And the time has come for a change.”

-

THEY were a vague crowd in the darkness. Galt pushed his way through, turning his face away from a beam of light from a pocket flash. Pinchot appeared, a white sweatband around his forehead. His face was taut; his tongue flicked restlessly at his lower lip. He handed Galt a small plastic-boxed talker.

“You’re on Team One, hitting Admin House. You worked a summer there as a messenger, you know the layout. You lie low until it’s secured. If Gray—I mean, when Gray and his team secure the port they’ll call in. Same with Tomkin, Pyle, Bergson—all the teams will report to you when they’ve pinned down their objectives. I’ll liaise with you—”

“Where am I supposed to hide while the rest of you are winning the war?”

“You take cover in the park while the rest of the team goes in. When you see their signal—we’re using survey flares—move in and take over the switchboard.” Pinchot beckoned to a tall, lean man. “Fry’s your Team Leader. You stick close to him until they move in. Okay, get going.”

Galt followed Fry and the other members of his team—two men and a girl named Teresa—as they threaded their way through the now-dispersing throng, turned east along the Outer Drive, heading for the park. The talker box muttered and crackled, monitoring terse conversations.

As they turned into Park Way, Galt caught Fry’s arm. “That’s a copflat parked up there.” He pointed to a police cart under a pole light a hundred yards distant.

“There’s nobody near it,” Fry said and shook off his hand. “Come on. We’ve got three minutes to get in position.”

The party went on, entered the park via a service gate, crossed toward the line of trees behind which the lights of Admin House glowed peacefully. They halted beside a fountain which tossed sprays up into colored light.

“There’s a gap in the hedge.” Fry pointed. “As soon as you see my flares, come in on the run.”

Galt nodded and took up his post behind a screen of shrubbery as the others slipped silently away. They reached the street, started across. A fine mist of spray from the fountain dampened Galt’s face. An imported insect alighted on his neck. He brushed it away.

The spotlights lanced out simultaneously from two points; one was aimed downward from the roof of Admin House, raking across the lawn, pinpointing the gate through which Fry and Teresa were just passing; the other, from the parked copflat, struck the group horizontally, threw stark shadows against the hedges. The two conspirators caught outside the gate froze for a moment, then turned and ran, their feet noisy in the silent street. An amplified voice boomed out.

“Stop where you are! Davies, Henderson! We know you, you can’t get away—” The voice broke off as light winked and a shot crashed from the gate. Fry was lying flat in the shadow of the ornamental gatepost. Galt saw another flash, but the second shot was drowned by the short savage roar of a police bullet-pump. Fry’s body was flung a foot into the air and hurled ten feet back like a bundle of rags. The two runners skidded to a halt and threw themselves face down in the street. Galt saw Teresa reach the front entrance of the government building; as she ran up the steps, the door burst open and two uniformed security men gathered her in.

Men in battle armor, hand guns ready, were swarming into the street, clustering at the gate and around the captives. Heavy footsteps sounded behind Galt. He hugged the ground, ducked as lights glared, playing across the shrubbery around him. A man went past less than six feet away.

At that moment, the talker box uttered a burst of static and a small clear voice said, “Power station secured. One man hurt and a couple of windows broken—otherwise no damage.”

The Security man who had just passed halted; gravel crunched as he swiveled, playing his light about. Galt eased back. The light flicked closer. He reached a large tree, got to his feet. A twig crackled.

“Stop there,” the Security man barked. Galt ran. A shot sang through foliage. He heard sounds ahead, veered right, crashed through a head-high hedge onto a bricked path. Two uniformed men standing fifty feet away turned toward him; he plunged around a bench, dived into massed foliage. It yielded and he was in the clear.

A tremendous blow on the calf of his right leg sent him tumbling. He rolled, tried to jump up, fell on his face. His leg was hot, numb, a dead weight. Scrabbling frantically with his hands, he dragged himself under a spread of juniper, felt the ground crumble beneath him. He rolled, fetched up with a thump in drifted leaves at the bottom of a drainage ditch.

The voices and footsteps came closer, but they seemed remote and unimportant now. Galt’s thoughts had leaped ahead, quite calmly, to the trial, the conviction, the prison sentence, the loss of his citizenship …

-

THE DARK was quiet now. Listening closely, Galt could hear distant voices over the rustle of foliage in the light breeze; but nothing stirred nearby. He moved his injured leg tentatively, discovered to his surprise that it responded, though painfully. He sat up, explored the wound. There was a neat hole in the mass of muscle below and behind the knee, a less neat hole to the left of the shin. A small calibre solid shot had gone through without hitting the bone. He rose to his feet. He could walk. He brushed leaves away, climbed out of the ditch and was confronting the hedge that bordered Government Street. Through a gap he could see the lighted front of Admin House. Uniformed men were on the terrace, on the lawn. The front doors stood open, brilliantly lit. Floods illuminated the lawns. A dozen copflats were in sight parked along the street.

At first Galt didn’t see it; then he did: Two-thirds of the Security Force was here, posted two deep around the front of the house; and he could see that the rear service entrance was equally guarded. But the small and inconspicuous entry at the side was shrouded in shadow. Insofar as Galt could see no Security men were near it.

The talker crackled and spoke: The Power Complex was in rebel hands. Pyle, at the port, called in: all secure. Bergson, sounding elated, reported the virtually unopposed seizure of the pumping station. The uprising had gone well—all but the most vital part. Administrator Blum and Major Jensen had concentrated all their forces here. They hadn’t been fooled for a moment. They knew all about the Committee’s plans and had been ready.

But there was that side door. Galt’s mouth was dry; his heart pounded painfully. It could be a trap. There might be half a dozen Sec men lying in wait for the mouse to take the cheese. But on the other hand, the door was little used; it was just possible that Jensen had overlooked it.

Galt could slip away now, return home, and be as surprised as everybody else when the news came out. Or he could put his neck solidly in the noose.

With a curse that was half prayer, he left his vantage point and, limping, slipped away along the hedge line.

-

FROM a clump of shadow between the library and the Agricultural Experimental Building Galt studied the scene. He had a better view of the side door from here. Nothing stirred there. To anyone not intimately familiar with the building, there appeared to be an unbroken mass of shrubbery along the east wall. Galt took a deep breath’ and stepped out, crossed the street openly, two hundred yards from the lighted gate of Admin House. He went back past the west wing of the elementary school, crossed the playground, came up along a path to a point fifty feet from the rear corner of Admin House, paused for a moment, then ran across a strip of open ground to the door. There was no alarm. He tried the latch, then pushed with his shoulder. The panel yielded slightly. He stepped back, kicked straight out at the lock. Plastic and metal shattered, the door bounced in. Galt slid inside, shut the door and stood in darkness, listening.

Voices sounded from the front of the house; somewhere a radio crackled and a toneless voice droned, too faint to make out the words. Feet clumped to and fro. There was a stair a few feet ahead. Galt felt his way in darkness, found the newel post, started up. He saw dim light above. On the second floor he looked along a carpeted hall. At the far end, a man in mufti with a paper in his hand emerged from a room, hurried away. Galt went on up.

The third floor corridor was illuminated. A uniformed Security man stood twenty feet away, fiddling with the mechanism of his blastgun. The man holstered the weapon, walked to the far end of the hall, lifted a house phone from its hook, began an inaudible conversation. He turned his back to Galt’s position, still talking. Galt slid out, eased silently along the passage to the intersection with the wide corridor off which’ the administrative suite opened.

Four Security men were in sight—two posted beside the ivory-enameled double doors, the other two at the main staircase. One of the men guarding the stairs descended a few steps to carry on a conversation regarding the whereabouts of someone named Katz. His partner leaned over the rail, his back to Galt. The two men on the door had their heads turned, following the exchange. Galt stepped out and walked silently and swiftly toward the door adjacent to the guarded portal. He was six feet from it when one of the men glanced his way, gave a startled grunt and grabbed for his slung blastgun, fumbled it.

“Here, you, where you think you’re going?” he blurted.

“Special messenger,” Galt said crisply.

He reached the door for which he had been headed as the second guard swung his gun around; Galt tried the knob; it turned; he plunged through as two shots racketed in the hall, gouging molten plastic from the doorframe. He spun, slammed the door, tripped the security lock system, heard armor sliding into place as a heavy body struck the panel from outside. Men hammered and shouted as Galt ran across the room, paused for an instant at the connecting door, picturing the slugs that would rip into his body if the administrator had posted guards inside his office as well as in the hall. Then he opened it and stepped through.

Administrator Blum was a plumpish man with graying hair; he sat behind his desk, his eyes on the hall door, an expression of surprise on his face. As Galt appeared he whirled, reached for a desk drawer. Galt dived, knocked the older man’s hand aside, scooped up the 2mm needier, aimed it at Blum.

“What—what—” Blum said, then collected himself. He straightened his clothing, fixed a stern expression on his round face, looked challengingly at Galt.

“Well? You’ve forced your way into my office for a reason, I suppose, since you’ll most certainly be taken into custody before you leave here.”

“Your Security men are overpaid,” Galt said. “They’re expert at harassing citizens but not so good when it comes to something complicated—like watching both sides of a house.”

Blum’s features flinched.

“I suggest you give yourself up at once, Andy,” he said. “You’ve made your point. HI personally look into the conduct of security affairs—”

“I’m not here to complain about inefficient police work/’ Galt said. “I’m here to take over the government.”

-

BLUM stared across the desk at Galt, who pulled a chair around and sat down. The pounding at the door went on; an intercom screen on the administrator’s desk buzzed insistently until Galt reached across and switched it off.

“Andy,” Blum said in a reasonable, kindly tone, “I’ve know your parents for thirty years. I remember the day you were born—”

“Make it Mr. Galt—Mickey.” Blum jerked as if he had been stung by a wasp. “I hardly think disrespect will advance your cause—whatever it is. Now, if you don’t mind, tell me why you’re here. I suggest you hurry, since my Security forces* will be in here at any moment—”

“I doubt that. Your locks are pretty solid.”

“You can’t possibly believe you can succeed in this abortive uprising!”

“We have the port, the power plant, Comm Center. The major seems to have overlooked a couple of bets while he concentrated on Admin House.”

“See here, Andy—Mr. Galt. You were always a level-headed lad, a good scholar, potentially a fine citizen and a valuable colonist. What are you doing mixed up with these anarchists? People like Daniel Pinchot—known radicals—soreheads—agitators—”

“Dan was a Sector Scholar. He may be impatient with the established order, but he’s no fool, Mr. Administrator. I’m mixed up with him because it was that or go on the way we’ve been going—and that wasn’t good enough.”

Blum’s face shifted to a look of grim determination. “I hardly think it’s the function of a handful of malcontents to determine unilaterally what is or is not good enough for the welfare of the colony as a whole.”

“And you are?”

“I was duly appointed by the Colonial Administration to carry out my function; I’ve been trained for this work; I have more years of experience in administration than you have of life!”

“I didn’t appoint you.”

“You’re intelligent enough to recognize the fact that specialists who’ve devoted their lives to the problems of government and administration are better qualified to run matters than a pack of—of amateurs who regard any restriction of what they consider their freedom and rights as intolerable burdens!”

“A pack of profit-minded bureaucrats and politicians who tell me I have to give up everything that makes life livable and devote a couple of years of hard labor to opening up new territories that we don’t need or want.”

“You’re a fool, Galt. You don’t know what you’re talking about! The economy must expand, or—”

“Or certain big corporations back on Terra won’t make as much as they’d like out of our blood, sweat and tears.”

‘That’s a childishly simplistic version of matters. Why—”

“You mean Parson’s Bay and General Logistics and North American Materials won’t show a profit from opening up the new sector?”

“Well—of course they hope to! And why shouldn’t they? They funded the great bulk of the developmental work, provided most of our specialized equipment, supplied technical experts—and still do—”

“All at a nice return on their money. And we do the work. Especially the five hundred names that got pulled out of a hat to open Sector Twelve.”

“So, like impatient kindergarten children, you’re going to take over the nursery and make it all one long playtime, is that it, Andy—Mr. Galt?”

“The mines will continue to operate, Mr. Administrator. We’ll still export—and don’t tell me how good and kind Terra is to buy our products. I know how scarce non-organically contaminated chemicals are today.”

“Suppose a squadron of Peace Enforcers arrives to restore order—”

“That won’t open any mines.”

-

BLUM gazed at Galt. It was quiet in the corridor now. A call light blinked on the big desk, ignored.

“You want all the advantages of what other men have built,” Blum said slowly, “but you want them without working for them, without effort, without commitment or obligation. Well, the Universe doesn’t work that way, my young friend. Nothing is free. Society isn’t withholding your birthright. You have no such birthright—not in the sense you’re apparently demanding.”

“I have the same birthright any animal in the wild has,” Galt said. “To take what I can get and hold,”

“So you’ll seize the granary and eat until it’s empty. But who’ll refill it for you, eh? You’ll grab the trideo set you’ve always wanted—but who’ll repair it, who’ll supply the power to run it, who’ll do the programing and the acting, who’ll pay the bills?”

“We will. We’re prepared to work as hard as required. But we intend to take the rewards for ourselves—for Colmar—including you, Mr. Blum, if you decide to stay—instead of sending them off-world for the benefit of corporate executives we’ve never met, who’ve never seen Colmar and never will.”

“It’s the arrogance of it that astounds me,” Blum said wonderingly. “We all have our obligations, Galt, whether it pleases us or not. The food you eat, the clothes you wear, the entertainments you enjoy, the education you were given didn’t just pop up out of the desert. Someone made them. They represent human ingenuity and effort—and you’ve reaped the benefits.”

“That’s a debt that’s passed along from generation to generation, Mr. Blum. A man owes nothing to the past. Life can’t demand payment for itself.”

“I’ve always thought you were a young man with a sense of decency, of justice, of regard for the rights of others. Tell me, Andy: if this—revolution of yours succeeds by some wild chance—what then? Will you rest easily with your loot? Can you justify to yourself theft on a grand scale, and settle down to enjoy your stolen goodies?”

“You’re taking the position,” Galt said, “that because the government exists—”

“Legally,” Blum put in.

“Because the government exists legally, that I’m therefore obligated to support it—or at least obey it. But I challenge that statement. Suppose the government were an outright tyranny: would I be obligated to connive at my own enslavement?”

“That’s absurd—”

“No. A man has a natural right that supersedes legal obligations. Overthrowing a legally constituted government is treason—unless you win. Because if you win, you change the laws. Then anyone who supports the old government is the traitor.”

“This is mere sophistry, Galt. You can’t mean—”

“The right to revolt,” Galt said slowly, as if thinking aloud, “is the most basic right a man has.”

“Activist jargon,” Blum snorted.

“Not if we win—and we have won, Mr. Administrator.”

Blum’s face flushed. “Nonsense. A pack of rabble-rousers couldn’t possibly have—”

“Wrong. We’re not rabble-rousers, we’re the rabble itself, Mr. Administrator. Mr. ex-Administrator. Check for yourself.”

Blum turned to his communicator panel, poked keys. His face tightened as no lights responded to his calls.

“You can still get through to Security barracks,” Galt said. “Call Jensen and tell them to put down their guns.”

-

BLUM punched out the code. The angry face of Major Jensen appeared on the desk screen.

“Mr. Administrator, thank God you’re all right!”

“Never mind that,” Blum said. “What’s the situation?”

“These hoodlums have invaded a number of installations, Mr. Administrator, but I can clean them out. Just the same, I’d suggest you get through to CDT Sector and request a pair of PE’s, triple UTU priority.”

“I’m afraid I’m not precisely at liberty to do that, Stig,” Blum said. He angled the pickup to include Galt, gun in hand. Jensen’s face jerked. “What—”

“The, ah, Revolutionary Committee seems to have outflanked us,” Blum said.

“Stand fast, Mr. Administrator,” Jensen said between clenched teeth. “My boys’ll blast their way in there and—”

“Lay down your arms, Jensen,” Galt cut in, leaning forward. “We hold every strong point In the colony—”

“I’ve got forty trained men on the grounds of Admin House,” Jensen grated. “You’ll never get out alive, you damned bandit!”

“Don’t talk like an ass, Stig,” Blum said calmly. “He’s out-manuvered you. It’s checkmate.” He looked at Galt. “What do you want from me, Andy?”

“Capitulate. Hand over control to the Committee and step down. I’ll guarantee your safe conduct—and Jensen’s, too, unless he does something stupid, like firing on our men.”

Blum stared levelly across at Galt. “Are you sure this is what you want? The responsibility—”

“Tell him,” Galt said harshly.

Blum turned to the screen. “Lay down your arms, Stig,” he said. “I’m signing a formal resignation in favor of Andrew Galt.”

-

TEN minutes later there was a brief clamor outside the door. Pinchot’s voice came over the talker.

“Open up, Galt! We’re in complete possession.”

Galt crossed the room and released the locking system. The door burst open. Gray came through, grinning a wide fox grin. He saw Blum, jerked up the weapon in his hand.

Behind him, a gun fired from six feet; Gray shrieked as the gun flew from his hand in a spatter of blood. He went to his knees, gripping his wrist, his hand welling crimson, as other men crowded into the room. It was Timmins who had fired. He came forward to stand beside Galt.

“Why the hell’d you do that?” Gray keened. “That’s the pig that had Fry and Len and Jeannie killed!”

“What did you expect him to do, give them a safe conduct?” Galt said tightly.

“Here, what’s going on,” Pinchot said, pushing forward. “You’d better give me the gun.” He held out his hand, the other hand resting on the butt of the pistol at his hip.

“I thought the idea was to improve government, not to start a reign of terror,” said Timmins.

“There’ll be no more killing,” Galt said. “Get rid of the gun, Timmins.”

Timmins tossed the weapon aside.

“Who are you to be giving orders?” Pinchot demanded of Galt.

“I’m the only one here with admin training. I’ll hold the office until we can stage elections—unless you want to start your new regime by killing me and maybe Timmins and a few others—and somehow I don’t think a purge will convince BuCol that you’re fit to run the Colony.”

Pinchot stared at Galt, eyes narrowed. Then he relaxed, thrust out a hand.

“Makes sense,” he said. “Let’s go, men.”

“You took a terrible chance,” Blum said after the others had withdrawn.

“I suppose that’s part of any revolution. Mr. Adminstrator.”

Blum sighed. “Call me Mickey.” he said. “There are a few things I ought to familiarize you with before I go.”

-

FOUR weeks later Galt sat behind the big desk, frowning at the papers before him. He shuffled through them, sighed. There was a perfunctory tap at the door and Pinchot came in.

“Afternoon, Mr. Administrator,” he said. “What are you looking so glum about? They elected you, didn’t they?”

“I’ll step down in your favor any time, Pinchot.”

“No, thanks. I never did like paperwork.” He eyed the stack on Galt’s desk. “In any case, the CDT and BuCol have both recognized you as the people’s choice. You’re stuck with it. I’m quite happy as Chief of Operations.” His genial expression faded a bit as he spoke. He swung a chair around and sat down.

“In that connection, Galt—what about the import program I outlined? You’ve had it three days now—”

“I know. Luxury goods. Official cars, cooler units, trideo programs.”

“So? Don’t we have the right to spend our money to suit ourselves? Isn’t that what the takeover was all about?”

“Sure. What money?”

Pinchot’s face went tight. “The price of the last shipment of ores, for example,” he snapped.

“It all went toward our credit deficit with Outplanet.”

“You expect me to believe that?”

“You can check the figures with Anderson if you like. No matter how many times we add them up they still come out the same. We’re running in the red—and what credit we still have has to go for necessities.”

“I heard all that from Anderson. That’s why I’m here. It’s not good enough, Galt. This isn’t why we threw out BuCol—just to carry on the same old swindle.”

“You can take over any time, Pinchot.” Galt slid a sheet of paper across to the other man. “My resignation, all ready*for signature.”

Pinchot stared at the document, pushed it away.

“I don’t get it,” he growled. “You’re spouting Blum’s line, the BuCol line—”

“It’s nobody’s line. It’s just the facts, Pinchot. We’re exporting X kilotons of minerals at Y creds per ton, and we’re importing Z creds worth of basic material. And we’re sliding a little deeper into the red every quarter.”

“They’re overcharging us, holding us up on prices—”

“Negative. They’re selling to us at seven percent under the open market scale. BuCol policy.”

“Then we can raise our prices—”

“Negative again. It’s marginal now. If our prices plus haulage go above costs of local procurement and refining, we’re out of business.”

“Then—what in God’s name can we do?”

Galt pushed another sheet of paper across the desk. Pinchot glanced at it, then stared at Galt.

“Are you right out of your mind? This is Blum’s Opening Order for Sector Twelve.”

“Wrong. It’s my order for opening Sector Twelve.”

“You can’t do it. The people won’t accept it. What will Gray and Williver—and Pyle and Tomkin and the others say? They—we—risked our necks fighting this same crazy scheme.”

“We need more income, less dependence on imports. We have to extend our usable acreage and expand our mining operations. If you can think of another way to do it, I’ll welcome the suggestion.”

Pinchot’s face looked slack and grayish. “Is this what we took over—the same old headaches, only worse?”

“Did we really take over, Pinchot?” Galt asked tiredly. “Or did they con us into standing on our own feet?”

Pinchot swore.

“I agree,” Galt said. Now let’s get to work. I need five hundred names for Sector Twelve. Any suggestions?”

The End